All these frameworks for building apps
very quickly have existed for a really
long time. Kotlin's existed for a long
time. Unity 3D for publishing games has
existed for a long time. And I mean, you
never like fully took the bar down to
zero. And even where you made it very,
very easy, you invite the hobbyist class
in who is just not really interested in
trying to build a business out of it.
So, you'll see disruptive change, but
it's going to happen a lot slower than
people think.
>> Hello, I'm your host David Barnard.
Today's conversation is shorter than
usual and will be featured in Revenue
Cat's State of Subscription Apps Report.
Each episode in this series will explore
one crucial topic and share actionable
insights from top subscription app
operators. With me today, Eric Seufert,
media strategist, quantitative marketer,
author, and investor. Eric currently
shares his musings in the Mobile Dev
Memo podcast, newsletter, and blog. On
the podcast, I talk with Eric about why
app economy disruption won't happen as
fast as everyone seems to think. How AI
is just as useful for defending against
copycats as creating them. And why the
real barrier to app success is still
distribution, not code. Hey Eric, thanks
so much for joining me on the podcast
today. David, good to see you. Hardly a
day has gone by in the past few months
where I don't have someone asking me,
"What's the future of the app economy?"
You know, freaked out that, you know,
AI's going to subsume all apps, that
you're only going to have ChatGPT, that
competition's crazy, that, you know, all
all manner of questions. So, I I've I've
like, gosh, like six or seven of the top
questions I get asked on a regular
basis, and
I wanted to chat through these with you.
I think of of all the the folks around
the industry, you are kind of the
foremost app economy expert, and I know
you're also super into AI these days and
following the industry very closely. So,
I thought it'd be great to have you on
to get your perspective on all this. So,
let let's just start with that first
question. Like, you know, it's so much
easier to build an app these days.
People are vibe coding apps in an
afternoon. What is What is a competition
angle mean for the app economy?
>> Well, first of all, thanks for having
me. Always appreciate the opportunity to
chat with you. Yeah, I mean, it's good
timing because, you know, we had um we
had AppLovin's earnings two nights ago,
and you know, the CEO talked about this,
right? So, what happens in a world where
uh the the sort of barrier to to entry
for for app publishing is is far lower
than it once was, right? Which Which I
mean, we're there now, but what happens
as it sort of like just continuously
descends?
And, you know, I think what AppLovin CEO
said, which is, you know, self-serving,
is that the key sort of function of
success is distribution, right? And And
I've made the same point, and you know,
I've been talking about this for a
couple years on Mobile Dev Memo, but I I
I made this point I don't know, 2023,
2022. A lot of these generative tools
are inflationary for for the app economy
and and for advertising generally,
because, you know, as just you get more
and more content being published, it
gets harder to stand out. I mean, that's
just like a pretty fundamental premise.
I mean, I don't think anybody would
disagree with that, right? And, you
know, I wrote a post on LinkedIn about
this a while back, because, you know, I
saw a bunch of people making predictions
around the start of the new year about
like mini apps and how these would take
off, and it's so easy to start an app.
Why don't you just everyone will just
create the apps that they need, and
these mini apps will become the the sort
of dominant interaction paradigm. And,
you know, they might Look, they might,
but you still have to get people to
discover your stuff. And if there's a
lot more stuff uh from which, you know,
to stand out, you have to work harder to
stand out, and that means advertising,
most likely. And if you look back at the
kind of history of these these
mechanisms that made publishing easier,
right? And in in the piece that I talk
about, I talk about the daguerreotype
photography that made it easier to sort
of get images in front of people, or you
know, And but like if you look at the
sort of like more recent history of just
blogging, right? The App Store itself,
right? When has user acquisition gotten
easier over time since 2008? Has it
ever? There's just There's There's this
long history of like, well, if it gets
easier to publish stuff, it gets harder
to get people to discover it.
>> At a more fundamental level, though,
does AI change our relationship to apps?
So, will people Will somebody just say,
"Hey ChatGPT, I want to run a 5K." And
ChatGPT's just going to coach them
through running a 5K instead of
downloading Runner or Strava or Couch to
5K or, you know, any of the hundreds of
running apps out there?
>> That's a really interesting question. I
think it's it's certainly a very
relevant question. I think it's TBD.
But, I think the the There's a bigger
question there, which is like, are you
saying, "Hey ChatGPT?" Who are you
saying, "Hey to?" Right? Because that's
not necessarily settled science that
ChatGPT just wins the category, right?
And so, the question is like, do you
just sort of Is it turtles all the way
down and up, right? Like, where do you
go for that information? Is it ChatGPT
or does someone unseat ChatGPT as the
go-to like verb for discovery, right?
But, my sense is Look, I mean, you
remember all of Apple's promises two
WWDCs ago. They They rolled out Apple
Intelligence. They talked about App
Intents. And none of that came to pass,
right? They They talked about this
overhauled Siri. None of that came to
pass. Now, that's not because it's
fundamentally impossible. That's just
because Apple didn't do a good job on
execution. But, like I don't know if you
remember with the App Intents stuff and
they they like mapped out this whole
series of interaction flows. And the
reason I remember this is I just I
remember writing about it. So, I just
looked it up before we started talking
cuz I I wrote a whole piece about like,
will this disrupt the app economy?
Because that's the same question people
were asking. If you've got App Intents,
do I need to interact with the app at
all? Like, if I need to do something in
that app, I'll just ask Siri, it'll go
in, it's got You've got the App Intents,
it'll hook into those, and it'll do
everything for me. And And what I, you
know, sort of hypothesized was like,
when this comes to fruition, and it will
at some point, is like, yeah, maybe the
category winners just run away with
everything because I'm not going to say,
"Hey Siri, open up one of my
ride-sharing apps and book me a ride to
the movies. I'm going to say open up
Uber because that's the dominant one.
Right? And so that could become, you
know, that could become the new dynamic
that we play in. But but I I don't think
I don't where I don't think we're going
to end up is like some sort of agent
that orchestrates everything for us and
there's no UI in any app because it's
all just APIs or just like MCP
interfaces. I don't think we're going to
end up there and like to your question
about like with Strava, my sense is like
the sort of chatbot interface that we
see now is limited in a lot of really
fundamental ways and at some point, you
know, people just prefer things that are
more tactile and more interactive. Now
maybe ChatGPT could replicate that. But
like that feels like a standalone
interaction use case that you'd have to
construct and I don't know that, you
know, certainly not in the current
interface, but I mean this stuff changes
all the time. But I could they just have
an interface for everything and the
running is, you know, learning how to
run or whatever tracking your running is
one and cooking is another and, you
know, whatever. My sense is like that
probably ends up not being super
meaningful for them in the same way like
why didn't Facebook do that? Because
ultimately like you're going to have
your core business and that's going to
dominate everything. And so building out
all these like use cases of specific
like functionality are not going to be
valuable enough for you to even do.
>> And I think people all you know the the
the kind of AI takes over everything
bulls are underestimating the
productization that takes place that all
the people at Strava who've been
building this product over years and
have that knowledge and have new
features they're continuing to add on in
a weekly monthly cadence. You just you
don't get that and so at some point
ChatGPT or some LLMs a better product
manager than human product managers and
it can just like build the perfect
interface. But I think we're a a long
way from that being true. But then what
about like vibe coding? Are people just
going to vibe code their own 5K app?
>> No. I mean, that's going to be like a
hobbyist effort. I mean, the thing is,
you know, coding has never really been
the core limitation of getting an app
done, right? It's, you know, and and I
mean, you'll see this. I mean, like
yeah, you could probably vibe code like
a recipe app or something that works
just as well as anything you get off the
internet, but but even then, probably
not, right? Because like it's a
specialization.
And it's managing the edge cases, and
it's having, you know, gotten user
feedback. I mean, if you're just vibe
coding something from scratch, it's not
going to be very good. I mean, you're
you're you're going in there with just
your intuition versus like an app that's
successful in the App Store is is
actually operating off of like this long
history of of feedback, right? And
that's it's been improved over time,
right? And that's why, you know, there's
a survivorship bias kind of thing there,
right? And so, look, I mean, you know,
this this was a question when a lot of
don't no-code tools were released to to
allow people to like, you know, publish
a game in like an afternoon, right? I
mean, like it's essentially no different
from using, probably actually easier
with the no-code tools to make a like a
very simple, superficial, hyper-casual
game than it is to do with ChatGPT,
because then you're still dealing with
Xcode and you publish you have to get a
DUNS number, as you know, you have to
get you know, get an Apple developer ID
and all that kind of stuff. I mean, you
know, and and I mean, you still have to
do that with the with the, you know,
like a Buildbox or something, but still,
it's it's it's it's a visual interface
for doing that. And that didn't really I
mean, none of those games were
commercially successful. And and and
like here's a good point that I see made
a lot, right? It's not mine. Name one
successful company that where their
product was built by Lovable. Name a
single one. Now, maybe there's a bunch
of people using their own recipe app
that they built with Lovable. Can you
name a single company and Lovable
apparently, according to them, has a lot
of ARR. I don't know what words they're
substituting in for that acronym, but
they say it's ARR, but name me a company
that is successful that is built off of
Lovable, and I don't think I can name a
single one. And we're still early, so
it'll be interesting to to see, cuz I I
do think there is potential for somebody
with good intuition and a good idea to
go into Lovable and build something that
that becomes a a great app that a lot of
people use. So, I don't think that's
outside of the realm of possibility in
the future. But But to your point, so
far we haven't seen any real breakouts.
What we've seen is people who are
already building apps and already had
that product intuition and do have some
amount of like code experience. They're
the ones really actually succeeding. And
then to your earlier point, it's also
the ones who figure out distribution.
It's It's not just about the code. And
so, yeah, you can pull something
together in lovable, but how are you
going to actually get it in front of
people? And that's still such a huge
barrier to entry.
>> I do push back and like maybe, you know,
someone would say like, "Okay, boomer."
to this, but I just push back
fundamentally on the idea of vibe coding
like an enterprise grade or scalable
product. I just don't think that's
possible. And I don't think that's ever
going to change, actually. I mean, you
just get you just encounter so many
dependencies with writing code. And it
has to be done really thoughtfully. I
mean, there's a reason if you talk to
like a senior software engineer, if like
they publish 200 lines of code in a day,
that's like a big day.
Right? The biggest part of the job is
not writing the code. It's actually
thinking through the implications on the
code base of what you're publishing. Is
it scalable? Is it sustainable? Is it
going to break something else? Like, is
this going to have to be rewritten in 3
years? Is it extensible? And, you know,
I don't vibe code in the sense that I
don't go into cursor and tell it to, you
know, build me an app. That would not be
a scalable thing. That, you know, could
build you a like an You hear this said a
lot. I mean, this is again, this is not
like some novel insight. But you can you
can build an MVP really quickly with
these tools. To build something that is
stable, that is scalable, that is
extensible, that is really difficult.
And so, I use I use Now, don't get me
wrong. I mean, I use AI tools all the
time for coding. But I want to see and
touch every single line of code that
goes into a a big code base. And I I
maintain a couple. And what I do is I'll
have it write a function for me, right?
I'll have it review code, right? But But
you talk to anybody who actually writes
software, ask them like what the most
fulfilling part of their job is. It's
deleting code. It's getting rid of code.
It's getting rid of old junk and knowing
that you can get rid of it without
breaking something. And that like
refactoring in that way, you know, what
you see a lot of people doing with like
vibe coding is they'll just start the
whole code base over. That clearly
doesn't scale for a large enough like a
large enough code base. A, it's going to
be more expensive than just having like
an software engineer working on it. But,
you know, you're just going to be
burning tokens all the time. But be then
you're just going to have to do that
again and again and again and you're not
going to have the consistency of a code
base cuz some things are going to change
each time you do that.
>> If you're going to build a meaningful
app, these tools as they exist today and
and they will get better, but they're
not going to support that kind of
scalability. They're not going to
support that kind of uptime. Yeah, and
and it just takes a lot more than is
still assumed in the AI hype cycle as of
today to actually build that kind of
great stuff. So, but you know, things
are moving quick. So, we'll see how much
better things get. As things do move
quicker and quicker though, the the one
thing I have heard a lot of people
asking about is copycats. Is that, you
know, a skilled developer using AI can
move quicker and so ripping off an app
like, you know, the entire, you know,
interaction paradigms. I mean, some are
even just ripping off style and like
assets from the apps and stuff like
that. How do you think about copycats
moving forward that if if you have a
success within a few days, there's going
to be tens of competitors for any app
that goes remotely viral?
>> A couple of things, right? So, one is
that's where true design intuition tends
to save you and tends to differentiate
you. And, you know, like you said, I
mean, people are just copycatting these
features or whatever. And so like, well
then people are just piggybacking off of
your true, you know, your sort of like
inherent design instinct or skill that
you've built up over a long time. It
doesn't necessarily be like an instinct.
They can't build new features that way,
right? I I that ends up differentiating
quality experiences from the mass,
right? If someone's just copying what
you've done pixel by pixel, there's not
much you can do to defend against that.
You see this a lot now with with
creatives, right? I mean, this has been
an issue for years, right? Like if you
have a winning creative, it's copied the
next day. And so, what do you do? You've
got to build a process to always have a
winning creative. That just shrinks your
lead time. And that's just a fact of
nature. And like that didn't stop user
acquisition. In fact, it just made it a
lot more important to have a scalable
process, right? An actual repeatable for
producing winners. And that what that
ended up doing was just accelerating
like the velocity of stuff that you
need. But I think it also made it a lot
more process driven, which is not
possible to replicate. Like if you're a
solo dev, you can't really replicate a
process cuz you don't see it. You can
replicate the ad, but you can't
replicate the process, which means
you'll always be eating the crumbs. And
that's where again, you see the primacy
of distribution, not production.
>> I have been really encouraged to see
Apple taking a hard stance on copycats.
They updated the rules of the App Store
recently, you know, saying copycats will
be banned. I've heard from from several
developers who had, you know, blatant
rip-off kind of apps where Apple very
quickly took them down. So, I do think
that there will be some onus on the
platforms. And this is where where it's
sometimes the platforms can be helpful
in in being able to police some of the
stuff. I mean, it's not going to be
perfect. And, you know, folks don't
always just completely rip you off. They
they take, you know, aspects of the
idea. But yeah, it's nice to see the
platforms getting involved in that way
as well. And that that provides a little
bit of defensibility, I think, in a in a
healthy way. Not preventing competition,
but preventing just being ripped off.
>> There's there's another piece of this,
too, which is like the AI stuff. It's
not one-sided. It's not just the
copycats and the scammers and the the
fraudsters that benefit from the AI. I
mean, there's the other side of that is
using AI to defend yourself against that
kind of stuff. So, you can use AI to
scan the App Store every day, look for
copycat apps. I mean, you know, we've
built stuff at Fabulous to to this. We
look at the App Store every day. We're
looking at stuff that's rising virally.
We're scanning it. We're looking at the
ads that they run. And so we have
defense mechanisms for this. So it's not
just one-sided that, you know, the
nefarious use case of AI always wins.
>> The last thing I wanted to touch on was
wallet share and willingness to pay. As
software gets easier and easier to
produce, and and it does seem like it's
just going to continue to accelerate
from here, is this deflationary on the
entire software ecosystem? You know,
apps are cheaper and cheaper to build,
so developers can charge less and less
for them. Do app prices go down? As AI
apps like ChatGPT and Claude and Gemini
and others take wallet share, are people
going to pay less for the other apps?
Like, where do you see things going
economically for apps?
>> There's there's got two things here,
right? So one is just, you know, I mean,
if you if you kind of take a much
longer, you know, sort of term view, I
mean, you could say, "Well, there's like
a lot of wealth fair effects from AI,
and it's going to drive the cost down a
lot of ways, and and it'll give people
more free time, and so there's just more
need to use more apps, but you've got
fixed income, but what what is
discretionary income mean in the world
dominated by AI?" And that's you're kind
of thinking like kind of very long-term.
I'm kind of if I you if you kind of
project out the next couple years, what
I think happens is, you know, people
have fixed discretionary income. They've
only got so many apps they can support.
Yeah, maybe you use price as a
differentiator, and you just race to the
bottom, but what does that mean? It
means ads. It means that's how you
monetize. And so everything's an ad
network on steroids, right? So you now
you've got everything running ads. Well,
okay, well, who's buying these ads?
Well, all that companies that didn't
exist before, but can via the sort of
miracle of AI, you know, launch a
product, and they've got to get
distribution. They've got to get
eyeballs on their stuff, right? And so
they're the ones buying all these brand
new ad units, right? And so you've got
this ads economy that's just
turbocharged as a result of this,
because you can't charge, because if you
charge, your competitors undercut you,
and so then you'll get no users, right?
And so therefore, the only way to make
any money is to show ads. And but won't
CPMs collapse if that's the case? No,
because there's a bunch of buyers now,
because there's way more software that's
trying to get eyeballs.
>> It's going to be fascinating to see how
how all this plays out in the next few
years, but I will say I think the
current kind of AI doomerism that there
will not be apps in a year is just not
true. And I think it's very overhyped.
As an app company today, you should be
keeping a very close eye on this. And
like you said, you know, running app
store queries on a daily basis to look
at defensibility. You should be
leveraging AI to move faster yourself.
You should be watching your back. You
know, there's all these things you
should be doing. But like freaking out
and saying like there won't be software
in a year, let me go start a farm, I
think is is very premature. This is I
think those of us deep into the AI side
of things and on Twitter and and that
sort of thing are exposed to it in a
different way than the rest of the world
is and are a little ahead of our skis on
on some of these predictions.
>> All these frameworks for building apps
very quickly have existed for a very
long time. Kotlin's existed for a long
time, right? You know, Unity 3D for
publishing games has existed for a long
time. And I mean, you never like fully
took the bar down to zero. And even
where you made it very, very easy, you
invite the hobbyist class in who is just
not really interested in trying to build
a business out of it. So, you'll see
disruptive change, but it's going to
happen a lot slower than people think.
>> That's a great way to sum it up. There
will be disruptive change, but it's
slower than the current estimates. So,
yeah. Well, Eric, it was so much fun
chatting through this with you. Anything
you want to share with the audience as
we wrap up? I know you've been blogging
and podcasting up a storm over at
MobileDevMemo.
>> Uh yeah, no, not really. Nothing
specific, but you can always find me at
MobileDevMemo or on on X.
>> Awesome. Thanks so much, Eric.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks so much for listening.
If you have a minute, please leave a
review in your favorite podcast player.
You can also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.
>> [music]